<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Locking tutorial</title>
  <author email="commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="Locking tutorial">

<p>The <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/package-summary.html">locking
package</a> merely consists of two interfaces for a <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/LockManager.html">lock
manager</a> and a <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/MultiLevelLock.html">multilevel
lock</a> and specific implementations. There is a <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/GenericLock.html">generic
implementation</a> of a multi level lock with a subtle, yet simple
compatibility mechanism. This mechanism allows to implement quite a
number of different lock types such as a read write lock which is
<a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/ReadWriteLock.html">provided
for covenience</a>, although very easy to implement. As already
<a href="index.html">exlained</a> in the locking agent can be any Java
object. Have a look at the simple <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/ReadWriteLock.html#acquireRead(java.lang.Object,%20long)">
method for acquiring a lock for read access</a> as a reference.</p>
<p>If you
need a single or pre-determined number of classes the generic or
read/write lock is all you need. However, sometimes you may not know
how many locks and which locks you will need in advance. In this case you can use the
lock manager with its <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/GenericLockManager.html">default
implementation</a>. The most <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/LockManager.html#atomicGetOrCreateLock(java.lang.Object)">important
method</a> is for either creating a non existing lock in a specified
resource or retrieving it if it was created before. It is important to
make this atomically so there is no chance of acciently creating more
than one lock for a single resource.</p>
<p><em>The whole trick is to have at
most one lock for a resource and have different compatible lock levels
for different agents acquiring the lock on that resource</em>.
</p>


<subsection name="Example: Fine grained locks in Jakarta Slide">

<p>Lets get to the first example which is how Jakarta Slide handles
fine grained locking in its WebDAV layer. Slide can store resources to
all kinds of stores which most likely have locks for consistency as
well. However, there is this generic locking to be very sure there are
no deadlocks, the behavior is similar for all stores and finally to
provide locking for stores that do not have locks of their own. All
locks must be set at the very beginning of a request and release at
the end of the request in an atomic 
block to ban the hazard of deadlocks. Slide does this with a simple
synchronized block, but to have something to show here we will exercise it
with a multi level lock. Such a lock is very simple and is merely
exclusive, it will look like this:</p>
<source>
GenericLock exclusive = new new GenericLock("Mutex", 1,
            new PrintWriterLogger(new PrintWriter(System.out), "Locking", false));
</source>
<p>
Now we have a lock called "Mutex" with the highest lock level of
<code>1</code> and a logger that simply writes to stdout. Different
lock levels and their compatibility is a special feature of
<a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/GenericLock.html">GenericLock</a>
and is explained there in detail. As we have one locking level, this
also is the only level we can possibly acquire causing an exclusive lock:</p>  
<source>
exclusive.acquire("Owner", 1, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>
<p>
This tries to <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/GenericLock.html#acquire(java.lang.Object,%20int,%20boolean,%20boolean,%20long)">acquire
a lock</a> of level one (=exclusive) for the agent 
"Owner". Parameters three and four tells the lock that it should block
the current thread if this lock level can not be acquired and that
this lock is reentrant. Reentrant means that the same agant can
require lock levels otherwise incompatible. Finally, there is a
timeout which is the maximum time the agent will wait for a lock. If a
lock still is unavailable after this time the method will return
false. In our case the request will (practically) never time out, we just wait until
we are served.</p>

<p>Now all requests to fine grained locks will be braced with the
above statement and the <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/GenericLock.html#release(java.lang.Object)">release
statement</a> after all fine grained locks are acquired:</p>    
<source>
exclusive.release("Owner");
</source>
<p>As a single agent ("Owner" in our case) can have at most one lock
level on a lock - only the highest will be effective - no more than
the agent is required as a parameter.
</p>

<p>Coming to the fain grained locks: Slide puts read and write locks
on resources accessed by WebDAV requests. As we really have no idea
with resources will be accessed until we receive the actual request we
use a lock manager which looks like this:</p>
<source>
public final static READ_LOCK = 1;
public final static WRITE_LOCK = 2;

LockManager lockManager = new GenericLockManager(WRITE_LOCK,
            new PrintWriterLogger(new PrintWriter(System.out), "Locking", false));
</source>

<p>Logs are the same as with the generic lock, they go to stdout. Before
explaining more details, let's see how we get a lock from that manager:</p> 
<source>
GenericLock lock = (GenericLock) lockManager.atomicGetOrCreateLock("/");
</source>
<p>This gives us the lock for the resource called "/" which of course is semantically
associated with the root of Slide's resource tree. The highst lock
level for the lock has been defined to two using the constant
<code>WRITE_LOCK</code>. Besides, it is good practice to use constants for the
lock levels in order to avoid unreadable code. Anyway, this returns a
lock that might have been created by this statement as well:</p>

<source>
GenericLock readWrite = new new GenericLock("/", 2,
            new PrintWriterLogger(new PrintWriter(System.out), "Locking", false));
</source>

<p>However, if we ask the lock manager for this lock the next time it
will not create a new lock, but will return the one created first
- preserving all lock levels already set. The assertion that all this
will be done atomically is very important for correctness and because
of this is reflected in the name of the method.
</p>

<p>The locks created by the above lock manager have two levels where
write is exclusive and read is shared. This means if there is a
write lock there can be no read locks and the other way
round. However, in the absense of a write lock read locks can happily
coexist with other read locks - they are shared - while write locks can not coexist with
other write locks - they are exclusive. This is very useful for server
locks as a there is no reason not to allow two GET requests to the
same resource at the same time. However, you should not allow a PUT
and a GET request to the same resource at the same time or even two PUT
requests. This means that none of the below statements will block</p>
<source>
readWrite.acquire("request1", READ_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
readWrite.acquire("request2", READ_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>
<p>
which would mean two requests called "request1" and "request2" can
read the root resource at the same time. Without releasing both of the
above locks the following write request will be blocked:</p> 
<source>
readWrite.acquire("request3", WRITE_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Advanced Example: Mixing fine grained with global locks">

<p>In Slide there is a search method that allows you to
query for a set of documents that satisfy certain search
conditions. When you execute such a query at least the result
documents and indices will be touched with read access. As we learned
before we need to acquire all locks on the documents accessed before
starting the actual request to guarantee correctness and eliminate the
hazard of any deadlock. Of course there is no way to determine which
documents this will be beforehand as this would require anticipate the
result. Effectively, we need a global read lock. Now, while there is a
global read lock no other request must be allowed to write
concurrently. More than one concurrent search request all having a
global read lock would be no problem, but all requests that write in
any way must acquire an exclusive write lock. Easy, one could say, so
we have a lock with levels READ and WRITE which is a
simple read/write-lock as we have seen above. However, this is not quite adequate as it
will demolish our fine grained locking mentioned before: writes would
now be globally exclusive again. So, what we want from our lock is
that an unrestricted number of search requests - in absence of any
write request - may be done concurrently. Additionally, an
unrestricted number of concurrent write requests - in absence of any
search request - should be allowed as well. Sometimes the solution to
a problem becomes obvious as soon as you have written it down - like
in or case: we need two read/write locks!</p>  

<p>
Now a search request would try to acquire those locks before it executes:</p>
<source>
public final static SHARED_LOCK = 1;
public final static EXCLUSIVE_LOCK = 2;

searchLock.acquire("search request", SHARED_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
writeLock.acquire("search request", EXCLUSIVE_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>
<p>Note that we now call lock level one SHARED and lock level two
EXCLUSIVE instead of READ and WRITE as it fits the semantics of these
operations better. Any write request will call these statements</p> 
<source>
writeLock.acquire("write request", SHARED_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
searchLock.acquire("write request", EXCLUSIVE_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>
<p>
as the counter part of the above. 
</p>

<p>That's it, isn't it? No, it is not. You might have already noticed,
that nothing has been gained. Now all write methods block each other
in the searchLock and all search methods block each other in the
writeLock! <em>Sigh</em>! This is not what we wanted, we just wanted
to disallow any search when writing and any write when searching. The
exclusive locks for write and search should have been
<em>compatible</em>. This is tough as the compatibility mechanism of
the generic lock is based on the order of the levels and the highest
simply is exclusive. Adding another lock level to make the formerly
highest non exclusive would only cause a mess as no one would
understand anything any more and most important it would still not be
compatible to itself. Luckily, next to the additional reentrant compatibility we
have already used above there is the so called <code>support</code>
compatibility of locks. When acquiring a lock level you can ask the
generic lock not to consider lock levels acquired by other locking
agents - such as the search method - for compatibility calculation if
they have the same lock level you desire. This results in the
following code which is the final version:</p>

<source>
searchLock.acquire("search request", SHARED_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
writeLock.acquire("search request", EXCLUSIVE_LOCK, true, 
            GenericLock.COMPATIBILITY_REENTRANT_AND_SUPPORT, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>

<p>and</p>

<source>
writeLock.acquire("write request", SHARED_LOCK, true, true, Long.MAX_VALUE);
searchLock.acquire("write request", EXCLUSIVE_LOCK, true, 
            GenericLock.COMPATIBILITY_REENTRANT_AND_SUPPORT, Long.MAX_VALUE);
</source>

<p>As much for our short round trip. More information about this additional compatibility can be found <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/sandbox/transaction/apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/locking/GenericLock.html#acquire(java.lang.Object,%20int,%20boolean,%20int,%20long)">here</a>.
If you still need more turn
to the mailing list, get through the Javadocs and as the last resort through
the sources ;) 

</p>
 
</subsection>

</section>



</body>
</document>
