<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Transactional file access</title>
  <author email="commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="Transactional file access">
 <p>Sometimes it may be desirable to save a single file or even a
 number of related files to the file system atomically. This means if
 you write something and an error occurs or for any reason you change
 your mind and rather want to cancel what you did. Consider your
 application fails in the middle of overwriting important data which
 neither gives you the old state nor the new one, but rather a
 corrupted one. Or only part of your data has been written leaving you
 with an inconsistent state.</p> 

<p>The <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/package-summary.html">transactional
file</a> package provides you with code that allows you to have atomic
read and write operations on any file system. The <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html">file
resource manager</a> offers you the possibility to isolate a number of
operations on a set of files in a transaction. Using the <a
href="../locks/index.html">locks package</a> it is able to offer you
full ACID transactions including serializability. Of course to make this
work all access to the managed files must be done by this
manager. Direct access to the file system can <em>not</em> be
monitored by the manager.</p>

<p>When you <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#startTransaction(java.lang.Object)">start</a>
a transaction you need to provide an indentifier to later refer to
this newly started transaction. You can also let an identifier be <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#generatedUniqueTxId()">generated</a>
for you. Calls to e.g. <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#readResource(java.lang.Object,%20java.lang.Object)">read</a>,
<a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#createResource(java.lang.Object,%20java.lang.Object)">create</a>
or <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#writeResource(java.lang.Object,%20java.lang.Object)">write
to</a> will need the identifier to know which transaction they belong to.</p> 

<p>Finally when you want to
commit the transaction call <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#commitTransaction(java.lang.Object)">commit</a>
or <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileResourceManager.html#rollbackTransaction(java.lang.Object)">rollback</a>
to undo all changes. The transactionality is achieved by first writing to
temporary files and upon commit moving or copying them to the primary
location. Locks and a delicate commit mechanism will assure that no
data corruption occurs.
</p>

<p>A fail safe <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileSequence.html">file
sequence</a> is the second main part of the file package. Just like
sequences known from Oracle or other relational database systems it
provides you with a unique ids. Each call to the <a
href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/transaction/file/FileSequence.html#nextSequenceValueBottom(java.lang.String,%20long)">next</a>
method will return a new unique long number and persists the current
value of the sequence to disk. This means when you shut down your
system and restart it you will still get no double
numbers, but the sequence will continue. Additionally, this sequence implementation is fail safe which
means when an error occurs while saving the value of the sequence to
disk you still are guaranteed not to get any double values. The file
containing the value is guaranteed not to be corrupted as well. 
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
